[Music]
Hi and welcome to this session on
viewing SQL details while performance
profiling. My name is Peter Boy. So
understanding SQL performance uh when
troubleshooting in the cloud without
direct SQL access can be hard. In this
release, we add the ability to track SQL
course calls uh both when using the
inclient profiler in the web client as
well as when capturing snapshots from
Visual Studio Code. This will help
consultants and developers and support
to faster identify and troubleshoot SQL
issues in customer production
environments. Uh providing a better
customer experience.
Before we delve into SQL details in
profile, let's do a short recap of what
profiling is. If you already used this,
feel free to skip ahead according to the
video chapters below.
Around 2020, which feels like ages ago
now, we launched the ability to capture
so-called snapshots, a form of uh record
and replay debugging in production
environments and capture those from
within Visual Studio Code. This also
allow capturing a performance profile to
view where time is spent during AL
execution.
To empower consultants and end users in
creating and analyzing performance
issues directly within the web client,
we launched the inclient profiler. In
2022 and since then profiling has become
essential to identify application
performance problems for customers,
partners and support and is the main
performance troubleshooting tool for
partners. As a recap, you can open the
tool from help and support uh with the
analyze performance or you can search
for performance profiler in tell me.
This opens a page that allows you to
start and stop a recording of a flow of
user actions in the web client uh that
you want to investigate any performance
issues in.
And then once you stop the interactive
recording, you can see the results and
you can see which extensions were
involved in the process, the total time
spent in execution. You can identify
extensions uh that might be slow. You
also get a detailed breakdown by
application objects and call tree to
drill down into the finer details. You
can learn more in the link uh that you
can also find below in the description
to make it easy and faster for
customers, consultants, prodevelopers,
partners and Microsoft support to
capture a profile um and thereby lower
manual uh collaboration and time to
mitigate. We introduced schedule
profiles a year ago and with these you
can capture performance profiles
automatically and non-interactively in
the background based on well-defined
rules triggering the capture. The rules
for when to capture profiles can be set
up by a partner. The user can then just
perform their daily tasks and then the
partner can come back and analy analyze
the profiles afterwards.
The schedule profiles is now the
recommended approach uh to profiling
performance issues because it's so easy
to set up and analyze afterwards.
So to learn more about schedule
profiling, you can view the launch event
uh from last year and you can find again
the link in the description below.
Now AL profiling works great, but it's
hard to investigate SQL performance
without direct SQL access. Thus in this
release we added SQL uh details in the
performance profiles and this helps
consultants and developers to faster
identify and troubleshoot SQL issues in
customer production environments uh and
lower then the time to mitigate and thus
increase the customer satisfaction.
So let's see how it works in practice.
So, we're now in the Business Central
web client, and I'm uh going to use the
schedule profiling to capture a profile.
So, let me create a new uh profiler
schedule. We'll call it just ble
and we'll activate it. We'll have it
start uh today. Um we'll just be me as a
user and we're going to log my
activities in the browser. I'm going to
set it to the smallest sampling mode and
make sure that it locks small things.
And then basically I've set up my
scheduling. And so now I can go into uh
something that I want to profile. So
let's now trigger my flow. So I actually
have a little helper function here that
that can help me do some work. So one of
the things is to run a long running uh
query. So I'll set up and create a lot
of records. And this will take 6 7
seconds. So we can see that uh in in the
profile. And now it's ready. And we can
actually go and just uh clean those out
uh as well just to see some additional
content. Okay. So let's go back to our
profiles. So here we have uh the results
from a couple of uh performance
profiling runs. If we look at the the
bottom performance profile and we scroll
a little bit, we can see that we spent a
total of 9 seconds uh but only a little
more than 1 second uh running AL, right?
Because most of the time which we can
now see in new columns is spent in SQL
calls. So about 6 and a half seconds. We
can see we did uh just over 60,000 SQL
calls. So that explains the time spent
um and also performance uh scheduling
or scheduling performance uh profiling
you can also use that for uh outbound uh
HTTP calls. You can also see the number
of outbound calls uh and duration of
those but we didn't do that in this uh
in this scenario. So we can actually
drill down into this uh profile and that
will show the view as you might be
familiar with uh on which extensions
took part uh in this flow. We can show
the technical information which allows
us to actually drill into the call tree
here. And if we expand everything, you
will now see that we have SQL
information uh underneath, right? And if
we drill uh further down or scroll
further down, uh we can see that the
majority of time 6 seconds here were
used uh on an action for setting up on
the page uh where we insert a lot into
the database, right? So this can
actually help you troubleshoot uh SQL
issues.
And also if we jump to Visual Studio
Code then you can see the same
information in Visual Studio Code. Uh we
can hover over this and see the full uh
SQL call and we can uh click to copy it.
To recap the demo, you can now see which
calls are made to SQL during a
performance profile and therefore better
assess whether bad performance is due to
ALE code inefficiencies or the resulting
SQL calls. For scheduled profiles in the
performance profiles overview page, you
can see the total duration of captured
SQL calls in code. uh you can see the
number of calls and you can also see the
duration of the platform calls when
drilling into a specific profile in the
client and whether it's recorded from
the interactive incline profile or the
schedule profiling you can see the
actual SQL calls that were made and you
can hover over them to see all of the
query and you can then copy it also
and SQL call information is also
available inside of Visual Studio Code.
when you've done uh snapshots or just by
importing the profiles. And you have to
note that only sampling mode is
supported. So this needs to be set for
the Visual Studio Code snapshot capture.
It's the only mode supported in client
and therefore implicitly set there. So
let's summarize the support. You can now
see SQL uh query details in performance
profiles. It's supported both inclined
in the interactive and schedule
profiling as well as industry studio
code and it's mapped to the parent a
call stack frames.
Uh in general there's two performance
scenarios that you might want to
investigate. Uh it could be
understanding individual performance
issues or box why a certain scenario is
low. It could also be as part of
developing you want to uh basically
instrument the code and understand each
of the SQL calls uh that happens to be
able to optimize as much as possible to
handle scaling or looping over code uh
many times and so uh we have had a focus
on the first scenario on solving
performance issues. Now we only support
the sampling mode as I mentioned not
instrumentation. uh that means that you
only get SQL information for the um AL
calls that are shown in the call stack
as part of the sampling. Uh but this
aligns with uh the inclient profiling
which is sampling only.
So as usual we have a lot of different
business central resources that you can
uh use. Um I already mentioned we have
several videos on this topic on YouTube
and you can as always give us feedback
on the ideas site
and you can follow uh weekly news and
announcements on the business central uh
page on LinkedIn. Thank you for watching
this session.